Have you ever wondered
if there are more natural ways
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today, the effects of
dairy milk on our health.
And we start with the
so-called “milk pus test”
(that's actually what it's called)
and what it tells us
about the U.S. milk supply.
Dairy cows might normally live
for about 20 years,
but they are typically
slaughtered for hamburger
after they're just
a few years old,
when they produce less milk
and their profitability drops.
But another leading cause
of cow culling is mastitis,
udder inflammation
and infections,
which affects 99.7 percent
of all dairy operations
in the United States.
Because of the mastitis epidemic
in the U.S. dairy herd,
the dairy industry continues
to demand that American milk
retain among
the highest allowable
"somatic cell" concentration,
nearly twice as much
as the rest of the world--
750,000 cells per milliliter.
The concentration
in milk from healthy udders
should be less than 100,000.
These somatic cells are mostly
white blood cells,
so, when you get up
to around 200,000,
which is, like,
a million per teaspoon,
the udder is likely
to be infected.
So, the somatic cell counts
in the bulk milk tanks
reflect the level of infection.
Basically,
if the bulk milk tank,
which can hold
thousands of gallons,
averages 200,000, then 15
percent of the contributing cows
are likely infected.
At a concentration of 400,000,
which is more in line
with international standards,
a third of the cows
are likely infected.
And staying within the 750,000
U.S. limit for Grade A milk
could reflect that
about two thirds of the cows
are infected.
Now, somatic cells are not
synonymous with pus cells,
as has sometimes been
misleadingly suggested.
Just as normal human blood
and breast milk
contain low levels
of white blood cells,
so does milk from healthy cows.
That's something we've known
for more than a century.
The problem is that many
of our cows are not healthy.
According to the latest
national government survey,
about one in four dairy cows
in the United States
suffers from clinical mastitis,
the second leading cause
of death on dairy farms.
This is why the average somatic
cell concentration of U.S. milk
is that
of a likely infected udder,
at 204,000 cells per milliliter.
How much actual pus
does that translate to?
Although the industry doesn't
like to talk about pus cells,
the fact that pus is present
in milk from inflamed
mammary glands is a given.
But what constitutes
pus in milk?
The quote-unquote
"milk pus test" was introduced
more than a century ago.
It pooled milk
from infected cows
that was estimated to contain
up to 2.5 percent pus by volume.
And we'd really like to see
no more than, like, 0.1 percent.
So, what does 204,000
cells per milliliter,
the national U.S. average,
translate to?
That's a million cells
per teaspoon of milk.
A million cells per spoonful
sounds like a lot,
but pus is really concentrated.
So, how much pus is there
in a glass of milk?
Not much.
If you take the national average
and subtract the number
of white blood cells
you might see in normal milk,
you get about 100,000
inflammatory white blood cells
per milliliter,
or about 25 million per cup.
Then it just depends on the
cellular concentration of pus.
Although straight pus may have
80,000 cells per microliter
or less,
to be conservative,
the most concentrated
I could find for straight pus
was about 150,000.
Note that's per microliter,
not per milliliter.
So, if there are about
25 million cells per cup,
and a microliter of pus
contains about 150,000 cells,
that would come out to be
about 150 microliters of pus
per glass of milk.
There are about
50 microliters in a drop,
so there'd only be a few drops
of pus per glass on average.
And you can apparently taste
the difference.
One of the major problems
associated with mastitis
is the flavor and texture
defects.
Milk with high somatic
cell counts looks the same,
but evidently doesn't smell
or taste as good.
The large amounts of pus
in mastitic milk
may be aesthetically
objectionable,
but it's important to note
this is not a food safety issue,
thanks to pasteurization.
The dairy industry emphasizes
that ingesting large amounts
of bovine white blood cells
has not been shown
to be harmful.
No matter how inflamed
and infected udders get,
the pus gets cooked.
But just as parents may not
want to feed their children
fecal bacteria in meat,
even if it's
irradiated fecal bacteria,
as the director of the
Food Policy Institute put it:
"Irradiated poop won't make you
sick, but it's still poop,"
parents may not want
to have their children sip
pasteurized pus.
In our next story,
we look at the role milk may
play in triggering Parkinson’s disease.
Parkinson's disease is a
neurodegenerative brain disorder
that affects millions of people.
What causes it?
Well, if you look at lifestyle factors
associated with Parkinson's disease,
the strongest dietary association
with increased risk of Parkinson's
disease is dairy consumption.
In fact, dairy products are the
only food group that has been
consistently associated with a
high risk of developing Parkinson's.
Five large prospective studies have
confirmed the link — including the two
Harvard cohorts, the Harvard
Nurses' Health Study and
other Health Professionals —
which followed more than a hundred
thousand people for decades,
in the largest analysis of dairy
and Parkinson's disease to date,
analyzing more than a thousand
newly diagnosed cases.
And all the studies found a link
between dairy and Parkinson's,
most finding a significant link:
about a 50% increased risk overall
in those drinking the most milk,
compared to those drinking the least
at a p value of less than 0.00001,
meaning less than 1 in 100,000
you'd only get a finding
that extreme by chance.
Okay, but why is there a link at all?
Despite clear-cut associations
between milk intake and
Parkinson's disease incidence,
there is no rational explanation,
concluded one review.
A year later though, we got a clue:
"Midlife milk consumption
and substantia nigra neuron
density at death."
What does that mean? Parkinson's is
caused when most of the nerve cells
in a critical part of
the brain are killed off.
So if you go back and see how
much milk people were drinking
in their 40s, 50s, and 60s, and then
look at their brains on autopsy
and count how many of these
critical neurons they had left,
in every single quadrant
neuron density was maximized
in those who
consumed no milk
and lowest in those who
consumed the most milk.
Even after removing the Parkinson's
cases, those drinking two cups of milk
a day had up to 40% fewer nerve
cells in that critical brain region.
What's in milk that could
be wiping out brain cells?
Among those who drank
the most milk, residues
of the pesticide heptachlor epoxide
were found in 9 out of 10 brains.
A-ha, so maybe the finding of pesticide
residues more commonly in the brains
of those who drank the most milk
could explain how milk could be
cause-and-effect related
to Parkinson's disease risk.
Now that's not the only
potential explanation.
Remember my video on how
meat contains that clumpy
neurotoxic protein alpha-synuclein?
Well, dairy products may contain
trace amounts as well, but we
don't have confirmation of that.
Could the milk sugar galactose
be the missing link?
That's what lactose in milk breaks
down into in the body, and galactose
is what's used to induce aging, to
experimentally cause aging in the brain.
When you drink it, the galactose
is picked up by your brain
within a few hours, and
for doses above 100 mg/kg,
it appears that galactose
can cause pathological
alterations in brain cells, similar to
those observed in Parkinson's disease.
And these quantities can be
reached and surpassed
with the simple daily consumption
of two glasses of milk,
the main dietary source
of galactose in humans.
And of all your brain cells,
those dopaminergic neurons,
the ones that you need
to retain to prevent Parkinson's,
may be more vulnerable
to galactose-induced damage,
galactose-induced oxidative stress.
Galactose may also explain
the findings that link milk drinking
with higher death rates.
Now you may be thinking, well,
duh, the saturated butterfat
is just cutting people's life short,
but higher mortality with higher milk
consumption is observed,
irrespective of the milk fat content.
Skim milk might be fat free,
but it's not lactose free.
Can't you just use
lactose-free milk?
What about Lactaid? That
has the lactase enzyme added
to make lactose-free milk, but it just
breaks down the lactose into galactose
in the carton rather
than in your gut,
so you're still ingesting the
same amount of galactose.
Perhaps no wonder then that
greater milk intake at midlife
may be associated with
greater rate of cognitive decline.
I mean, researchers use galactose
to create brain aging in the laboratory.
Administration of D-galactose,
a metabolic derivative of lactose,
has been extensively used
to mimic cognitive aging
through oxidative stress
in animal models.
Compared to those who said
they "almost never" drink milk,
those drinking more than a glass
a day appear more likely
to suffer a global decline
in their cognitive function.
Finally today,
how to reduce the risk of premature
death from dairy consumption.
In my video
on milk and bones,
I discussed
this set of studies,
following a hundred thousand
people for up to two decades,
finding a 60% higher risk
of hip fracture
among women who drank
a lot of milk.
The researchers suggested it
might be due to the galactose,
which is a breakdown product
of the milk sugar lactose,
based on the fact that people
with high levels in their blood,
because they were born with an
inability to detoxify the stuff,
can end up
with weakened bones.
But that's not all
galactose can do.
Galactose is what scientists use
to cause accelerated aging
in lab animals,
since it's so successful
at mimicking aging
by inducing degenerative changes
in the brain,
heart, lungs, liver,
kidney, etc.
"Life-shortened animals
showed neurodegeneration,
mental retardation,
and cognitive dysfunction,
diminished immune responses
and a reduction
of reproductive ability."
And it doesn't take much,
just the human equivalent
of one to two glasses worth
of milk a day.
However, humans aren't rodents.
For example, we've known
for nearly a century
that you can cause cataracts
in rats
by feeding them lots
of lactose or galactose,
but the epidemiological data
is mixed
as to whether dairy
is doing the same in people.
The Swedish studies didn't
just look at bone, though,
but milk and mortality.
More milk was associated
with more death.
In women,
three glasses of milk a day
was associated with nearly twice
the risk of dying prematurely.
The medical journal editorial
accompanying the study
emphasized that,
given the rise
in milk consumption
around the world,
the "role of milk in mortality
needs to be established
definitively now."
With the then-largest-ever study
on milk intake and mortality
suggesting such adverse effects,
Harvard researchers stepped in
with three of their cohorts
to form a study twice as big
to see if the earlier findings
were just a fluke.
Following more than
200,000 men and women
for up to three decades,
they confirmed the bad news.
Those who consumed more dairy
lived significantly shorter
lives.
Every half serving more
of regular milk a day
was associated with
9% increased risk of dying
from cardiovascular disease,
11% increased risk
of dying from cancer,
and an 11% increased risk
of dying
from all causes put together.
This is all the more remarkable
since milk drinking
is typically associated
with healthier habits,
like more exercise
and less smoking and drinking,
though they did try to control
for all these factors.
Of course it does matter
what you eat instead.
This Harvard analysis published
in the New England Journal
of Medicine,
found that swapping dairy
for meat,
red meat, poultry, or fish,
would not be expected
to do your body any favors,
and you would be expected
to live longer eating dairy
than eggs or processed meat.
It's only when you swap dairy
for plant-based sources
of protein
did they find a significant drop
in mortality risk.
When all of the milk
and mortality studies
are put together,
it appears
the excess mortality risk
is limited to regular as opposed
to low-fat, like skim milk.
This suggests it may be more
of a saturated fat issue,
though that doesn't explain why
soured, or fermented milk
appears to have
the opposite impact.
So maybe it's both the butterfat
and the galactose.
A randomized crossover study
of low-fat dairy,
fermented dairy,
and unfermented dairy
found that study subjects
had significantly higher
IL-6 inflammation levels
during unfermented
regular dairy weeks
compared to when they were
switched to either
the fermented
or low-fat dairy products.
The fermentation process can
eliminate some of the galactose.
As we age, our ability
to detoxify galactose
declines by as much as 40%,
which would make it
even more important
to avoid dairy later in life
if indeed galactose
is the culprit.
But if galactose
does its dirty work
through oxidation
and inflammation,
might increased fruit
and vegetable intake
help mediate some of the harm?
In animals,
galactose-induced aging
can be slowed by fruit
and vegetable consumption.
For example,
feeding rats blueberries
can decrease the brain damage
induced by the milk sugar.
Might it be able to help
with the higher levels
of oxidative stress
and inflammation found
among human milk drinkers?
Unfortunately, women drinking
three or more glasses of milk
a day had more than twice
the risk of hip fractures
compared to women drinking
less than a glass a day
regardless of whether
they were eating more, or less,
fruits and vegetables.
But, those high milk consumers
consuming five or more servings
of fruits and vegetables a day
did reduce their chance
of dying prematurely
to just 60% greater
than those drinking less milk,
so antioxidant rich foods
may be able to modify
the elevated death rate
associated with
high milk consumption.
Highly influential
advocacy organizations,
such as the US National
Osteoporosis Foundation
or the Europe-based
International
Osteoporosis Foundation,
continue to push dairy, drugs,
and calcium supplements,
despite the countervailing
evidence that I've reviewed.
Why do they keep pushing dairy,
drugs, and supplements?
Perhaps because their
objectivity is compromised
by the influence
of their commercial sponsors
that include companies
that market, you guessed it,
dairy, drugs,
and supplements.
Most recent reviews
on dairy and osteoporosis
in the English-language
medical literature
were found to be written
by those with ties
to the dairy industry.
The primary justification
for inclusion of dairy
in federal nutrition
recommendations
is based on
purported bone benefits
that are not supported
by the available evidence.
What if dietary guidelines
were fashioned
without commercial influence?
In 2019, Canada decided
to exclude industry reports
and stick to the science
in the formation
of their new dietary guidelines.
What a concept.
Major changes
include the new emphasis
on plant-based food intake,
limiting junk,
and...the removal
of the dairy food group.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
All proceeds from book
sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.